Um.
Microsoft Original Director
So, without further through. Let's get start it!
Good morning! I'm so happy to be here. And
so honored to be keynoting the DDD Taiwan
Conference this year. Especially with the
theme being footprints of pioneers. So I
may not be a pioneer but I love the idea
of footprints, and everybody's learning journey
for Domain-Driven Design. My name's Julie Lerman,
and I must admit not only am I not in Taiwan
with all of you right now which I wish I were
Um, but I've also am providing you a recorded talk,
I'm recording this talk for you in advance just
so that we don't have any issues with internet
since I'm so far away! Where I am is in Vermont
in the U.S.. However I am online with you all today
and will be available in the really really fun
community area so I am here but at the moment as
I'm speaking I am not. So I have um I am definitely
somebody who's very passionate about Domain-Driven
Design but I have spent a lot of time thinking
and talking and worrying about how to make
Domain-Driven Design more accessible to people
it's a really really big topic and that's what
I'll be talking about today so the title of this
talk is getting to domain of design pragmatic or
principled and this will hopefully be helpful to
you whether you're on your own journey into
learning domain or uh Domain-Driven Design
or if you are somebody who's already interested
and excited about it and really looking for ways
to help others learn about Domain-Driven Design
and I do want to give a little background about
the first reason that I created this talk
I was at Domain-Driven Design Europe
and I do know that a lot of you are .Net developers
so you might know me also from my involvement with
entity framework and I was doing a workshop
on entity framework at the DDD conference
and after my workshop and some feedback from
a few people I wrote this tweet about um
entity framework core and Domain-Driven Design and
used the word purists in the tweet and um I got in
a little bit of trouble, not trouble it just a
few people were a little annoyed by my use of
that term. Um so you know perhaps purists was one
word or I could have also used the word principled
instead of purists but you know the reason I wrote
that tweet and the reason I am giving this talk
to you today is to really look at if we could be
more pragmatic about how we approach Domain-Driven
Design and learning Domain-Driven Design but
still retain the principles and the important
guidelines and guidance that Domain-Driven Design
gives us and I use those words guidelines and
guidance very intentionally. I think a lot of
people look for rules and definitions and when
we have rules and definitions that definitely
shuts out a lot of people because they're worried
if I'm not following the rules exactly. Um so I
want people to be able to use bene use DDD well
and benefit from it, um but not worry about having
to be an expert from end to end of Domain-Driven
Design before you begin trying to leverage it
in the way you approach building your software.
I have been with clients I even spent a
week at a client at a very large company
with a few teams that had gotten to the
point where they did not want to hear
anything about Domain-Driven Design anymore
and that was because of the way it had been
presented to them by other members of their
teams and these are more of the people who um
the the people who were sharing it with them
were of the mind that you need to know everything
all at once before you can start and they
just did not want to hear about it anymore,
um and you know so I'm really familiar with this
problem and I would like to say after the week
that I spent there kind of you know backing
up and giving them a new approach and a new
entrance ramp uh to Domain-Driven Design that they
felt so much better about it and I left there with
them being really eager to continue their DDD
learning. So I want to play a game I want you
to play a game and granted this is something I
usually do with a live audience when I'm standing
up on stage and you're all together in a room and
I thought long and hard about how to recreate this
when we're virtual. So this is what we'll do
normally what I would have you do is face the
person next to you and play a mirror game where
one person is drawing let's see like if I can do
this in the if I'm my hands in the camera if I'm
drawing the number two right as I'm drawing in and
looks right to me it's totally backwards to you
so I will be your partner and I just want you to
try this you'll have to touch the screen but just
do it in the air follow along with me and I kind
of have to look over to make sure I've got this
right so I'm not going to be looking right at you.
So try to follow me as I draw the number two so
your your finger following my finger right so it's
it's like you're in a mirror so there's the number
two now we'll try the number four so here's four
right and I'm I'm writing it so it's perfectly
fine for me and then I'm going to draw the number
six so go ahead and follow me oops I went off the
camera there sorry now I'll do an eight I'll start
up a little higher to get a little over to the
left okay. So now I'm going to draw the number
eight uh let's do that again I don't know if I
did it right because I was trying to make sure
okay there's eight and now one more we'll
do 10 okay so 10. Let me go one and zero so
how did it go? Uh was it a little harder than you
expected it to be because everything was backwards
um but you know of all those two four six eight
and ten what do you think for you what was the
easiest thing to draw now when I've been in
rooms of people and ask um sometimes I hear
four sometimes I hear eight but most often
the answer which makes most sense to me is ten
and the reason is because you're not really
doing anything backwards when you're drawing
a one if if you're drawing it just a simple
straight line one right that's really easy
and you know drawing a circle whether whichever
way you draw it is is that is pretty easy and
so I think of this game and and I do want to
shout out to my friend Jessie Shternshus who
I saw her do this um at another conference
where she was talking about using improvisation
to help developers unlearn some bad habits so I
adapted it for this so this isn't about unlearning
it's about learning. And so you know if you think
about having to try to write all those numbers
backwards like all at once and it might have been
a little confusing and a little overwhelming but
perhaps you had a little relief when you got to
draw the one and the zero right and and this to me
is an interesting expression of how I think it's
more helpful for people to learn new concepts
especially something as big as Domain-Driven
Design. S o what if I had started by just asking
you to do a mirror of the number one right that's
pretty easy and pretty easy to be successful at
and maybe even one and zero or maybe we should
account and we could start with zero and do the
one right once you've done those like oh okay
now I know how to do those and maybe you've got
confidence to continue on to you know to do a
two and a four and a six and an eight um and
and this is really for me the idea of learning
one thing at a time you know one thing where a
you're getting confidence from it and b it's
actually something that can be useful without
having to know the whole thing is how I approach
uh sharing Domain-Driven Design with other people.
A nd and how if you're new to DDD I hope
you'll be happy with learning that way
and if you're somebody who's been doing
Domain-Driven Design for a while you know
think about this as you're sharing your love of
Domain-Driven Design with other people. So for me
starting with just pieces of Domain-Driven Design
right the core principles of Domain-Driven Design
instead of saying you know you need to read Eric
Evans DDD book from page one all the way to the
end before we can begin on a project. Now I'm not
saying that you shouldn't have an understanding
of the whole concept of Domain-Driven Design
that's really important but to really have pieces
of it that you're using and implementing
it's hard to learn all of them at once
but you can still benefit by learning and
understanding a piece of it and applying
that and implementing that. And then you can
start growing your understanding and your use
of the practices and patterns that we've learned
from Domain-Driven Design as opposed to saying
hey here is the mind map of Domain-Driven Design
and this is what we're going to learn right like
I would turn around and run out of the room like
oh my gosh it's too much and I have to say after
going through the process my own little by little
you know gaining more knowledge and more knowledge
I have a pretty good understanding of this mind
map but at the beginning when I first started
learning about Domain-Driven Design there was
no way it was overwhelming and it was confusing.
So you know or as opposed to having a picture
of the mind map if somebody you know came into
the room and said okay roll up your sleeves, we're
going to do Domain-Driven Design, right? Or if you
know you've never heard of DDD before done any of
the practices, okay we're going to use an aggregate
root and we're going to use value objects and
we're going to use this and we can use that and
it's just like ah this it's so many terms and
so many concepts and new things to understand.
So one of the things that I do a lot when
I'm working with clients who are learning
about Domain-Driven Design instead of talking to
them about aggregate roots like you know at the
beginning, aggregate roots, and value objects, and
and aggregates, and bonded context, and ubiquitous
language, and all of these things which you know
I understand this is the very first talk you're
hearing at this conference so you'll be hearing a
lot about these things throughout the next couple
of days in the sessions and the workshops but
what I do is instead of saying okay now we're
going to start using aggregate roots I don't
tell them the term I show them right I show them
some code or maybe not even code, we don't you know
we don't really start with the idea of the code, we
start with the idea of the business problem that
we're trying to solve. So I kind of map some of
that stuff out and we can talk about it and they
understand it and then I let them know you know,
by the way, and I should say I don't happen to
start with this particular example. Um but you
know whatever whichever concept from Domain-Driven
Design it is. I'll start by showing it to them. And
once they have an understanding of it, then I
tell them okay in Domain-Driven Design, this
has a particular name and it's important to
understand those names those that terminology
so that you can have conversations with
other people about what you're doing
and that parallels really interestingly to
one of the concepts of Domain-Driven Design.
It's referred to as ubiquitous language. Don't
worry too much about what that is you'll learn
more about it later. Um and you know that the term
ubiquitous so it just means a language that's used
everywhere. And uh Domain-Driven Design itself
in its terminology has its own language, so it
is important in Domain-Driven Design we use that
ubiquitous language so that we can communicate
with each other about the domain, about the
problems that we're solving. So as we step back as
practitioners and we need to talk about what it is
that we're what it is that we're doing in terms of
the architecture or the modeling. It is important
to use and understand those terms so that we can
all be on the same page and and have clarification
on it. I have been fortunate to be at a number of
conferences where Michael Feathers has spoken
and at one of them he was talking about inside
out architecture, and I thought about that um
with respect to how I share Domain-Driven Design
with people and it seemed to resonate right um
instead of starting you know it's the same idea
instead of starting with a language and with the
terminologies and then showing what structure that
represents. I go the other way around, right? I show
the structure, and then I introduce the language. So
for me that that's how I see it as being inside
out. And also, I know a lot of people like to use
the gardening analogy, but it works really well
and it works for me I like to garden, but I'm not
a master gardener. This is, this is about where I am
at these days although um even painting all those
tires so beautifully might be above my pay grade
as they say, but you know this is, this is how you
can start right so this may not be master gardener
level, wonderful garden, right? But it's it's still
a thing of beauty, and and it's achieving a lot
by creating beauty, even though it's not, you know,
amazing gardening like maybe all those plants
are in their own little pots you buy them in a
pot and you just stick them in there, I don't know.
But there's a beautiful little garden, right? So
with a little bit of knowledge about gardening,
you can still benefit and you can still achieve
something beautiful. And you know maybe eventually
someday depending on how much free time you have
um you'll get to this kind of a garden,
right? But if you you know think about that
with all of the different things you need to
understand and know about Domain-Driven Design,
right? You can start with a small amount and then
you know if you're on a team there may be other
people who have more knowledge and you can work
together and they can mentor you as you gain
more knowledge but you don't have to have that
expertise going in. So, one of the most important
concepts within all of Domain-Driven Design is
the bounded context. And it's interesting that in
recent years and so Eric Evans wrote the book on
Domain-Driven Design and it was published in 2003.
So when I say in recent years maybe within
the last 10 years, he has said numerous times
that if he were to write the book over again he
would start with a concept of bounded context,
because it's really so critical to Domain-Driven
Design. But it's also the most potentially
misunderstood concept in Domain-Driven
Design. And I totally agree because I also
had some I had to take a path into it
right I did not understand it right away.
So the really high-level explanation of bounded
context is when you're you're looking at your
whole domain and you know the whole big business
problem that you're trying to solve. And it's just,
it's too many things going on all at once. So what
we do with the bounded context is we break it down
into smaller solvable parts, so aligning that
to cells, right? These are cells and each of
these cells is very bounded or constrained
by the membranes, these orange membranes that
surround them, and those membranes prevent
the bounded contexts for those cells
from communicating directly with each other,
from having to know about what's going on
in the other cells, right? And having having to
have all of that complexity added to their own
problems, right? Um and and also you know
leaking information from one to another.
So with the cells like with a bounded context you
can just focus on one small part of the problem
and just don't worry about all the rest, because
like those membranes, Domain-Driven Design gives
us wonderful ways that people have a lot of
experience with of communicating between those
cells giving you know taking information from one
cell and sharing it with another cell. So we those
patterns all exist. So you can actually say let me
just focus on this one problem, right? I'm not going
to worry about those other problems, and suddenly
life does become simpler! I promise you, I even
apply the idea of bound, you know these boundaries,
uh you know, after dinner and there's dishes and
food to put away and this problem going on in that
and just like okay I'm just going to focus on one,
and oh okay, I can handle washing the
dishes, right? Put them in the dryer,
right? Okay, now I'll go well maybe I should put
the food away first. Okay, so I'll take that problem
first, right? But there's, there's so much value to
this concept of just breaking a big problem that
is maybe overwhelming down into small problems
and then each of the small problems you can solve,
right? And much less stressful, and then and then
worry about the interactions of them because we
have all those patterns so you don't have to worry
about that. So I've kind of driven towards this
in this explanation of my path to Domain-Driven
Design. Before I truly understood bounded context,
I definitely grasped the idea of boundaries
and benefited from boundaries greatly.
Before I was knowledgeable enough to really
understand that context, and implement
bounded context, and all that evolves around
that um I'll take myself as an example. So I
I know a lot of you are .Net developers and you
know so you knew know about entity framework
um in the early days of the entity framework
the way it worked was that you pointed it to a
database. The database might have you know legacy
database might have you know 700 tables and
25 000 relationships and you point it there
and create one big huge model from that.
And I would just look at that and say this
this just can't be right! It's so complex,
right? So with the idea of boundaries uh that you
know one of the early things I understood from
Domain-Driven Design. I was able to look at these
uh entity domain models and say: oh wait a minute,
you know I don't need to look at all of it at
once. Let me just create a small model, that's just
you know these things, because this these things
all relate to each other and they're transactional.
And I can just focus on that, and then you know
slowly I'm pulling apart this huge model and have
maybe I have a lot of, a lot more things
I'm dealing with, but each of those things
is so much simpler that it's overall a
huge benefit to to have broken it down.
Um and you know I do like to think of myself as a
canary in the coal mine. I don't know if you know
this analogy um in in coal mines. The air isn't
very good down there, and poor little canaries they
would take these little canaries down into the
coal mine. And if the canary could still breathe,
then it was, you know, good chance that the
coal miner would be safe. But if the canary
died. Sorry, um, then they knew it was it was
terrible really, um, anyway now I'm really
sad about the canary so we'll just go to, um! So I
feel like that with a lot of technology, right? Uh I
feel like if I can learn it, you can learn it! right?
Entity framework, I figured it out here I'll show
you how to use it. Um and you know, I had my path
to Domain-Driven Design. It was not the same as
you know it wasn't I read the whole book and then
I was like, oh okay, I understand it all now I'm
gonna do it it was little by little by little. So I
actually want to share with you what that path was.
So I understood the concept of domain, right? Like
the the big the business, the business problem
you're working on or maybe part of that
business problem that you're trying to
solve. So I understood that that I was focused on,
and then I understood the concept of boundaries,
right. And interestingly Domain-Driven
Design when you read different books
or courses, etc. They don't really focus on
boundaries they go right into bounded context
and you know so I looked about a context, but
I didn't really get all of it. But I understood
that concept of boundaries and you'll see it
wasn't an immediate next step to bounded context.
From there I started really understanding this
idea of each uh each of the bounded contexts even
though to me it was just something with a boundary
could use should use separate databases and that,
you know, that also sounds like like oh that's
crazy why would you do that but you know we hear a
lot more about that with microservices as well. And
uh, you know the capability I think uh coming from
somebody who's been programming for 30 years
the idea of oh multiple databases, you know,
sql server, and thinking how expensive it is, and
everything like things are very very different now.
Um but understanding why like not trying to put,
you know, share everything all in one place how um
how much simpler things get and these
problems just start sorting themselves out
by, you know, this this deep separation concerns by
saying, you know, we're going to have our this data
stored here, and this data stored here, not try to
make it related, and not try to normalize it, and
not try to share it for, you know, have data that
has lots of different meanings, right? So um within
these boundaries things have specific meanings and
with those meanings will store them in their own
database, And again, trusting that, you know, our our
technology provides uh not only our technology but
ideas from Domain-Driven Design give us
all kinds of ways to share that data so that
didn't seem to. I finally realized it took a
while to realize it wasn't as big a deal as
I originally thought. Then um, and again, I'm not
here to teach you all of these different things
because you've got two full days of sessions and
workshops, but you'll hear these things so the next
thing that I really understood in Domain-Driven
Design. I started really understanding the idea
of the aggregate root, so like the um in an um in
a graph of objects, the objects that's responsible
for all the business logic and the rules of that
transactional unit. From there I finally started
understanding value objects. And this is where I
always have to stop, and say value objects were
the hardest thing for me to get my head
around. The further away I get from that,
the harder it might be for me to understand how
hard it was, but I will never forget how hard it
was. And that I learned, I think it was like five
completely different examples from books, from
conference talks, from conversations that I had
with different people or from different people.
Um completely different perspective on
describing what a value object was, right? And
you know, I got the first one and I didn't quite
get it, and the second one, I didn't quite get it
it wasn't until that fifth one and I'll tell you, I
was at I remember Microsoft TechNet Conference
I was at a TechNet conference I was speaking,
but Jimmy Nilsson was also speaking, and he gave
an example of value objects that had something
to do with eggs and an egg curtain, and I can't
remember exactly what it was. I should go back and
find a video of that. But there was something about
his explanation. Now it wasn't his explanation that
was oh finally the perfect explanation, but it but
I had the ability to take what he was saying, and
put it together with all the other descriptions
that I've heard, and then putting them all together.
I finally,finally went, oh! I get it! Okay! I get it!
Right? So the reason I'm telling you that is here I
am giving a keynote talk at a DDD conference, right?
I want you to understand it doesn't just come
to me like that. It's just just because I'm here
giving a conference talk and a keynote doesn't
mean that you know oh I'm one of those people
where everything's really easy I'm persistent.
So you know, I kept at it, um, and you know it's
just, I just want you to know that. So you know
if you don't get it right away, don't stress out
about it, don't beat yourself up about it, right?
It's just it's normal and it's, you know, it's
just a matter of, uh, hearing an explanation that is
designed in the same pattern that your brain works,
right? And that was me I had to take all these
others together. Um, now when I teach Domain-
Driven Design, especially you know the beginning getting
started I have a Pluralsight course on it that I
did with my friend Steve Smith. Um, I tried to
take the way that now I understand it to try to
see if that is a more helpful way for people to
first understand it. Anyway, so value objects, um,
I just, you know, like any of the other pieces
here, don't stress out that. By the time I heard that
fifth explanation. I already had all this other
stuff kind of under my belt like I got it and
understanding those things helped me finally
get to my aggregate root. And I've mentioned
this before ubiquitous language, this was something
that, um, I think I had a hard time with it mostly,
because I saw the term too much, too many
times before I understood it and every, you
know, and I started getting like those those, uh
developers at that client like: I don't want to
hear about ubiquitous language anymore, I don't
understand it and you just keep saying that word
what is uh uh the princess bride you keep saying
that word but I don't think you really know what
it means well the people who are saying it did
know what it means it's just you keep saying
it, I don't understand! Um, now I understand, right?
And, and again it was just part of, part of my path
putting together all of these things, bounded
context finely gelled and bounded context
is actually very tightly tied to ubiquitous
language, interesting. And it's important to have
that language so that when you're talking about a
particular problem, or problem set everybody's on
the same page and you all know what you're talking
about because oh we're in the context of um uh
selling boots, right? So you know when we
talk about heal, right? These are, these are
things in our business, right? That's a, that's
something within our business we talk about,
you know, certain aspects of manufacturing boots, we
we know that those specific to manufacturing boots
some of those words the things that
you do when you're manufacturing boots.
You might have the same word when you're
manufacturing computers, but it means something
totally different, because it's a whole different
set of problems. And the reason I'm harping on
this a little bit right now is because I real
I've learned that there's a lot of people who
when they first learned about ubiquitous language,
they thought it meant throughout the entire domain
across every single bounded context. So I just want
to leave you with that, right? That, that's it's per
bounded context. So, all of these things helped
me understand better and better a bounded context.
Um, and then anti-corruption layers are just one
of the patterns that we have for communicating
uh, data that needs to go maybe from one bounded
context to another messages or events that need to
to go. Um and I have that one in there specifically
because again, you know, I had this kind of brain
freeze on anti-corruption layers. Interestingly,
not on what they were for but the actual name. I
always would stop and go ACL, right? I remember ACL
and then I would say ACL anti-corruption layers
whenever I'm like trying to talk about them. So,
all of these things little by little over time,
you know, with the support of other people
that I'm working with enabled me to finally
grasp that full mind map of Domain-Driven Design,
right? But along the way, you know, understanding
boundaries before I understood bounded context
already benefited me a great deal, um, you know,
and and throughout. So I wanted to talk a little
bit about, um, when I go in to work with a client,
and usually they're refactoring they're dealing
with some legacy code, and I just wanted to give
you an idea of what it is that I'm doing, and
how I approach that so uh from for for you
what this could mean is, you know, if you're on
a team and you're dealing with legacy software,
and uh, you know, bringing the ideas and the
guidance from Domain-Driven Design into the mix.
So usually these clients are dealing with
legacy software and what this might mean for you
is you know if you're in that situation, and you're
trying to help your team or help others use Domain
-Driven Design ideas to begin looking at the
software and how you might start refactoring it.
This is, this is somehow sometimes my approach.
So one of the things I'll do is work on,
you know, and and look for these ideas as you go
through the next couple of days. I'll, I'll work on
a, you know, a transactional bundle of objects
that go together. For example, if you're doing
sales, um, an order with its line items, right? And
an order we have certain rules about that order.
So what I do we do is we'll look at just
that, right? That group of objects that travel
uh through your application together. And
look to see if we can find boundaries,
right? Like, for example, you might say: well,
it's a customer with an order with line
items and products, right? And now we've got
all the problems of maintaining the customer.
Suddenly involved in this problem and, you know,
so start I start looking for boundaries and and
exploring that, and we just do this on a whiteboard,
and you might keep turning it on its head, right?
Like just different perspectives, but I don't talk
about aggregate roots, right? I don't talk about
value objects, and, you know, bounded context. I
just say let's look at, you know, your domain
and let's look at the problems you're trying to
solve. And you know, let's just try to get some
new perspective on them along the way. Then I'll
say: oh by the way, we refer you know when we're
talking using Domain-Driven Design ideas we
refer to this as an aggregate root or we refer
to this as an aggregate or we refer to this
as a value object or an entity or whatever.
Then you know, and then we just dig in and do
a little more work, go a little more deeply,
right? And again, just whiteboarding without terms,
right? And then say: oh by the way, the thing that
we just did this is you know in DDD. It's called
this and this and that. So I intro slowly introduce
the terms, um, as they get, uh, more accustomed to the
concepts. So we just go back and forth like that.
And eventually, you know, their garden, this
is more my style garden a little more of
like, I think it's called an English garden
a little, a little more wild, but you know, and
it grows your your understanding of Domain-Driven
Design grows, and the, um, your ability to apply
these ideas to the software you're
building and gain the benefits
that Domain-Driven Design gives us which, you know,
in my mind is to make my life simpler, right? To
destress the subtitle of Eric Evans book is
tackling complexity, right? Tackling complexity.
So we take this like this might look complex,
right? But it started from something small,
um, and you know another thing I want to point
out, um, some. It's not that it's a criticism of
this idea of learning Domain-Driven Design little
by little, and I've heard other like DDD gurus,
um, talk about, you know, do is is this approach is
it really Domain-Driven Design? Or is it something
like Domain-Driven Design light? But when they
say that, right? I think well that sounds kind of
negative like it's just a lightweight version,
maybe maybe they even say l-i-t-e which, you
know, l-i-g-h-t that's a wonderful thing, right? It's
shining light on things, but what they're saying is,
you know, like a a lightweight version of DDD, right?
Which is not a terrible thing, right? In in a lot of
people's minds. But I prefer to think of it as DDD
core, right? The, the core elements of Domain-Driven
Design like, you know, really like you know learn
that bounded context learn how to, how to identify
boundaries, then you know and then dig in deeper. Um,
I so I do prefer referring to it as as DDD core
and then a few last things that I want to leave
you with, um, that, you know, I think is really
important to share when when you're talking about
Domain-Driven Design. First of all, again, as you'll
learn throughout the next couple of days, DDD
is really made up of two really important areas,
one is strategic design where you do all this
planning, right? where you figure out, where these
where those boundaries line, and then figure out
how things relate to each other within those
boundaries, and then figure out you know how you're
going to enable communication of messages or data
between those boundaries. So within strategic
design, you know, that one of the most important
things is about client collaboration
which doesn't end with strategic design,
and you know, focusing on, you know, when you are
looking at the big big problem of your domain
and you divide it up into smaller problem
sets really, you know, identifying what is the
most important piece that drives your business,
right? What's unique about your business that
uh really makes money, right? That, that like what
is the most important thing and really focusing
on that, um, you know, and then for me, reducing
the complexity which also reduces stress.
Discovering those bounded contexts and boundaries
and discovering that ubiquitous language within
those bounded contexts. Then the other big piece
of it is once you've done all that strategizing,
it's really time to start thinking about how
you're going to put the code together, right?
How you're going to implement these bound, these
domains, these bounded contexts that you've defined
during the strategic design, and you know, it does,
it can really lead you to writing better code, um,
let you know value objects really are a beautiful
thing. And uh the same client that I went to where
everybody like was saying: I don't want to hear
any more about Domain-Driven Design. The end of the
last day, one of the developers and this is a very
very intelligent guy came up to me and said, you
know, I never really thought about value objects
before, and now I realize how beautiful they are,
and how important they are. And now I'm so excited
about learning more about what DDD gives me, right?
Enables me to build better software like I almost,
you know, some people would be like might dropped me
I was like almost crying. When he said that, um,
and you know, there are really interesting things
to learn about how we define relationships
between our entities in Domain-Driven Design.
Aggregate root is, you know, all of these things as
I learn them and as I see other people learning
them on the aggregate roots, and, and the this
importance uh one of the things that TDD really um
helps is to eliminate like side effects, like
unexpected unanticipated side effects, right?
Because you don't have things that are just
connected all over the place, right? Things are
really bound, right? So these these are the things
that you define as your... these are the benefits
that we gain as we're working inside the bounded
context and doing the implementation the tactical
design, so things that you can look forward to as
you're learning more about Domain-Driven Design. So
I hope this uh talking about these things will
help you as you move through the the talks and
the workshops of the next couple of days. You're
going to be inundated with all kinds of really
amazing ideas and it may feel overwhelming.
But don't, don't stress out about them, right?
You can just kind of take it all in and it'll be
back there when you're ready for it. But, you know,
find the things that really make the most sense
to you and those are where you can start with.
So have a wonderful conference, um, and I
look forward to chatting with you in the
virtual community room. It looks like so much fun
I've had a little tour of it. Thank you so much!
Okay, thanks, thanks Julie for
her excellent speech and let's give her
a round of applause silently
in front of your computer.
Okay, thanks Julie! Okay! silently! Yeah, Okay. So I
love Julie's speech very much, her speech very much!
Especially when the idea of don't tell just do and
find some boundaries first, and forget about all
those dragons and get rules value objects first, and
focus on the domain. Okay, the next part will be our.
uh, we'll turn to Slido, and we have 10 more minutes
for our Q&A sessions. Let me share my screen. Okay!
So if you haven't, haven't post your
question on the, on the Slido, you have
some minutes to do it, and you can vote
your favorite questions. Okay! So...okay!
So, Julie, so, the first question is
could you explain, could you explain more on the
difference between sub domain and bounded context?
Yeah, that's actually a great question, uh,
because, um, sometimes a sub... when you identify
the sub-domain that has the same boundaries as the
bounded context. So, so quite often they look like
just the same piece of your domain, but there are
times, and that's probably the most normal where
once you've identified the sub-domain, and
then... so I'm just going to back up a little bit.
So sub-do... the the sub-domains are the things
are what you look for first. You don't start
by looking for bounded context you look to
identify the different sub-domains, and then
you start talking about the sub-domains, this is
when the ubiquitous language starts evolving.
And it's from that ubiquitous language
that you start defining the bounded context.
So quite often the, uh, perimeter, right? That,
that which is the sub-domain aligns perfectly
with a bounded context. But sometimes you
might want, you might find that you need to
implement that sub-domain as two different
bounded contexts for one reason or another. Um, and
interestingly, the... I've got a a Pluralsight course
on called, uh, Domain-Driven Design fundamentals
that I did with Steve Smith, and when we first did
the course, we interviewed on video, on camera. We
interviewed Eric Evans, and um, this was one of the
questions we asked him, and he also, his, his answer
was more, uh, deeper than what I've just said. Um, but
if you do happen to watch that course you can also
see Eric, um, with the, with the way that he helps
explain how sometimes it's the same and sometimes
it's different. So a little hard to deeply answer
that, right? Now but I hope that helps a little bit.
Okay thanks Julie! Oh, that's a well explanation. If
you have more interested, please check the videos
with the interview with Eric Evans.
Yeah! Yeah! Pluralsight is free this week
through, um, through the seven. It's been
all week and through Sunday, the 17th.
It's free! So, if you don't even have a Pluralsight
subscription, you can still go watch it.
Wow! That's big surprise! Thanks!
Thanks for sharing that.
System with a history of more than 20 years. How
can we replace that system through DDD in stages
interactively? Please. Yeah! Um, that, this is, uh, a
very common conversation, a very common question.
Because, uh, most often, people are dealing with
legacy applications, right? Not everybody gets
to start with a brand new idea and, and build
it up from scratch. And you, you know nobody can
just say: Okay, we're just going to replace the
whole thing all at once, right? It's, it's hard,
it's like impossible to do. There are actually
quite a few patterns for, for doing that, um, and
people talk about that a lot when they talk
about microservices, when they talk about
evolving their system into microservices. But,
you know, you need a plan. There's no question
about that, and absolutely it's something that, you
know, uh, you would need to do iteratively. Um, but
first you know it, you need to just kind of step
back. I think the most important first step is
to look at the business almost like it's brand
new, like try to understand it from a very new
perspective, because the one thing you don't
want to do is just rewrite the same logic.
That was how you thought about it 20 years ago, and
then just write it, you know, in new code, right? It's
your the best opportunity to really step back and
re-consider how data would, you know, how the data
is moving around, how, um, you know what the problems
are, what are the most important problems to,
to focus on. Um, one other thing I want to
say about that is when I'm helping people
learn these techniques, um, what we do is we
look for that low hanging fruit if you know
that phrase like the eat kind of the easiest thing,
but that's not for the implementation, that's just
for learning. Like we do the easy thing
because it's something easy to learn with.
But, um, doing that strategic design can also help
you identify what the, you know, what your path is
through the changes. What's, what's the most you
know, what is the most effective thing you can
create the most quickly, or, um, you know, as you're
learning. So, uh, that that's a huge question, so
hopefully that's a little bit of an idea of where
to begin. Yeah! Thanks Julie! That's very very useful!
Do you have an experience to work with a group
of people that is not applying DDD on server side?
Like mobile or desktop? Can you share something
about that? Sure! Um, personally, I haven't been
involved in that. However, um, I've had a lot of
conversations with people who have been doing
it. There are even a few people who, uh, speakers and
and people who are writing and training that focus
on, and it's kind of unusual focus on Domain
-Driven Design at for the front end which is
really interesting, you know, applying the ideas.
But one of the most interesting stories that was
shared with me was with somebody, um, who again with
a they had a legacy app and the back end of that
app worked perfectly! And they didn't want
to mock with it, but they needed to have
a a modern front end, they needed to modernize
the front end for their users because
it was just so old-fashioned, and they wanted
something new. So, what they ended up doing was, um,
because they wanted to leave like their old db2
database intact and their old Cobol code intact
they built, they found a Cobol developer to
write an API in front of the Cobol logic.
And so their new user interface just talked to the
API, and then the API just let the Cobol logic do
everything that it's always been able to do.
And they did something similar in front of
the database they put an ORM, uh, not entity...
I don't think it was a entity framework, but an
ORM in front of db2 that allowed them to query
out of the database without having to know how to
interact with db2, and they were then able to
apply, uh, and use really modern, not just modern
tools, but modern software practices with the new
stuff. So it was really really interesting and I
really think of that as Domain-Driven Design
thinking to have come up with that solution.
Okay! Thanks! That's very insightful and
knowledgeable! Okay! So it's 9:50 here, so
our first speech ends here, and let's give Julie
a very big big thanks! Okay, thanks Julie! Nice to
meet you! Hope we can see you next year or in a few
years. Yes! Thank you so much for inviting me. It was,
it really was a pleasure. Yeah we are also
honored to have you here. So, thank you! Bye-bye!